Chapter 64.
Stubs supper.
Stubs whale had been killed some distance from the ship. It was a calm,
so forming a tandem of three boats, we commenced the slow business of towing
the trophy to the Peekquad. And now, as we 18 men with our 36 arms and 180
thumbs and fingers, slowly toiled hour after hour upon that inert sluggish
corpse in the sea, and it seemed hardly to budge at all, except at long
intervals, good evidence was hereby furnished of the enormousness of the
mass we moved. For upon the great canal of Hang Ho, or whatever they call it in
China, four or five laborers on the footpath will draw a bulky freighted
junk at the rate of a mile an hour. But this grand argy we towed heavily forged
along, as if laden with pig lead in bulk.
Darkness came on, but three lights up and down in the Peekquad's main rigging
dimly guided our way, till drawing nearer, we saw Ahab dropping one of
several more lanterns over the bull works. Vacantly eyeing the heaving whale
for a moment, he issued the usual orders for securing it for the night, and then,
handing his lantern to a seaman, went his way into the cabin, and did not come
forward again until morning.
Though in overseeing the pursuit of this whale, Captain Ahab had invinced his
customary activity to call it so, yet now that the creature was dead, some
vague dissatisfaction or impatience or despair seemed working in him, as if the
sight of that dead body reminded him that Moby Dick was yet to be slain. And
though a thousand other whales were brought to his ship, all that would not
one jot advance his grand monoomanic object.
Very soon you would have thought from the sound of the Peekquad's decks that
all hands were preparing to cast anchor in the deep, for heavy chains are being
dragged along the deck and thrust rattling out of the port holes. But by
those clanking links the vast corpse itself, not the ship, is to be morowed,
tied by the head to the stern, and by the tail to the boughs. The whale now
lies with its black hole close to the vessels, and seen through the darkness
of the night which obscured the spars and rigging a loft. The two ship and
whale seemed yolked together like colossal bulocks, whereof one recines,
while the other remains standing.
Footnote. A little item may as well be related here. The strongest and most
reliable hold which the ship has upon the whale when mored alongside is by the
flukes or tail. And as from its greater density, that part is relatively heavier
than any other, excepting the side fins.
Its flexibility, even in death, causes it to sink low beneath the surface, so
that with the hand you cannot get at it from the boat in order to put the chain
around it. But this difficulty is ingeniously overcome. A small strong
line is prepared with a wooden float at its outer end and a weight in its middle
while the other end is secured to the ship. By a droid management, the wooden
float is made to rise on the other side of the mass. So that now having girdled
the whale, the chain is readily made to follow suit, and being slipped along the
body, is at last locked fast round the smallest part of the tail, at the point
of junction with its broad flukes, or lobes.
End of footnote.
If Moody Ahab was now all quiescence, at least so far as could be known on deck,
Stub, his second mate, flushed with conquest, betrayed an unusual, but still
goodnatured excitement. Such an unwanted bustle was he in that thestead
Starbucks, his official superior, quietly resigned to him, for the time
the sole management of affairs. One small helping cause of all this liveless
in Stub was soon made strangely manifest.
Stub was a high liver. He was somewhat inmperately fond of the whale as a
flavorish thing to his pallet. A steak.
A steak. Air I sleep. You dagu overboard you go and cut me one from his small.
Here be it known that though these wild fishermen do not, as a general thing,
according to the great military maxim, make the enemy defay the current
expenses of the war, at least before receiving the proceeds of the voyage.
Yet now and then you find some of these Nantuckers who have a genuine relish for
that particular part of the sperm whale designated by stub, comprising the
tapering extremity of the body.
About midnight that steak was cut and cooked, and lighted by two lanterns of
sperm oil, Stub stoutly stood up to his spermicetti supper at the capston head,
as if that capston were a sideborn. Nor was Stub the only banquitter on whales
flesh that night, mingling their mumblings with his own mastications,
thousands on thousands of sharks swarming round the dead Leviathan,
smackingly feasted on its fatness. The few sleepers below in their bunks were
often startled by the sharp slapping of their tails against the hull within a
few inches of the sleepers hearts.
Peering over the side you could just see them as before you heard them wallowing
in the sullen black waters and turning over on their backs as they scooped out
huge globular pieces of the whale of the bigness of a human head. This particular
feat of the shark seems all but miraculous. How at such an apparently
unassalable surface they contrive to gouge out such symmetrical mouthfuls
remains a part of the universal problem of all things. The mark that they thus
leave in the whale may best be likened to a hollow made by a carpenter in
counterinking for a screw.
Though amid all the smoking horror and diabolism of a seafite, sharks will be
seen longingly gazing up to the ship's decks like hungry dogs round a table
where red meat is being carved, ready to bolt down every killed man that is
tossed to them. And though while the valiant butchers over the deck table are
thus cannibally carving each other's live meat with carving knives all gilded
and tassled, the sharks also with their jewel hilted mouths are quarrelomely
carving away under the table at the dead meat. And though were you to turn the
whole affair upside down, it would still be pretty much the same thing, that is
to say, a shocking sharkish business enough for all parties. And those sharks
also are the invariable outr rididers of all slave ships crossing the Atlantic,
symmetrically trotting alongside to be handy in case a parcel is to be carried
anywhere, or a dead slave to be decently buried. And though one or two other like
instances might be set down, touching the set terms, places, and occasions,
when sharks do most socially congregate, and most hilariously feast, yet there is
no conceivable time or occasion when you will find them in such countless
numbers, and in gayer or more jovial spirits, than around a dead sperm whale,
mured by night to a whale ship at sea.
If you have never seen that site, then suspend your decision about the
propriety of devil worship and the expediency of consiliating the devil.
But as yet Stub heeded not the mumblings of the banquet that was going on so nigh
him, no more than the sharks heeded the smacking of his own epicuran lips.
"Cook, cook! Where's that old fleece?"
he cried at length, widening his legs still further, as if to form a more
secure base for his supper, and at the same time darting his fork into the dish
as if stabbing with his lance. "Cook!
You! Cook! Sail this way! Cook!"
The old black, not in any very high glee at having been previously roused from
his warm hammock at a most unseasonable hour, came shambling along from his
galley. For like many old blacks, there was something the matter with his knee
pans, which he did not keep well scoured like his other pans. This old fleece, as
they called him, came shuffling and limping along, assisting his step with
his tongs, which, after a clumsy fashion, were made of straightened iron
hoops. This old ebony floundered along, and in obedience to the word of command,
came to a dead stop on the opposite side of Stub's sideboard, when, with both
hands folded before him, and resting on his two-legged cane, he bowed his arched
back still further over at the same time sideways inclining his head, so as to
bring his best ear into play. Cook, said Stub, rapidly lifting a rather reddish
morsel to his mouth. Don't you think this steak is rather overdone? You've
been beating this steak too much, cook.
It's too tender. Don't I always say that to be good, a whale steak must be tough.
There are those sharks now over the side. Don't you see they prefer it tough
and rare? What a shindy they are kicking up. Cook, go and talk to them. Tell them
they are welcome to help themselves civily and in moderation, but they must
keep quiet. Blast me if I can hear my own voice. Away, cook, and deliver my
message. Here, take this lantern.
Snatching one from his sideboard. Now then, go and preach to him.
Sullenly taking the offered lantern, old fleece limped across the deck to the
bull works, and then, with one hand dropping his light low over the sea, so
as to get a good view of his congregation, with the other hand he
solemnly flourished his tongs, and leaning far over the side in a mumbling
voice, began addressing the sharks, while Stub, softly crawling behind,
overheard all that was said. The fellow critters, I was ordered here to say that
you must stop that damn noise there. You hear? Stop that damn smacking of the
lips. Massive stubs say that you can feel your damn bellies up to the
hatchings, but bygore you must stop that damn racket.
Cook here. Interposed Stub accompanying the word with a sudden slap on the
shoulder. Cook. Why damn your eyes? You mustn't swear that way when you're
preaching. That's no way to convert sinners. Cook. Oh, dad. Then preach to
him yourself solemnly turning to go. No, Cook. Go on. Go on.
Well, then beloved fellow critters.
Right, exclaimed Stub approvingly. Coax them to it. Try that. And Fleece continued.
Though you as all sharks and by nature very warous, yet I say to you fellow
critters that that warousness, top that damn slapping of the tail. How you tink
to here? Suppose you keep up such a damn slapping and biting there. Cook cried
Stub, collaring him. I won't have that swearing. Talk to him gentlemanly.
Once more the sermon proceeded.
Your waraciousness, fellow critters, I don't blame you so much for that is
nature and can't be helped. But to govern that wicked nature, that is the
pint. You is shark certain. But if you govern the shark in you, why then you be
angel? For all angel is nothing more than the shark well governed. Now look
here, brethren. Just try once to be civil, a help in yourselves from that
whale. Don't be tearing the blubber out of your neighbor's mouth. I say is not
one shark right as tutor to that whale.
And by gore, none of you has the right to that whale. That whale belonged to
someone else. I know some of you has very big mouth, bigger than others. But
then the big mouth sometimes had the small bellies. So that the brigness of
the mouth is not to swallow with but to bit off the blubber for the small fried
sharks that can't get into the scrge to help themselves.
Well done, old fleece, cried Stub.
That's Christianity. Go on. No use going on. The damn will keep a scing and a
slap in each other masses Stub. They don't hear one word. No use of preaching
to such damn glutton as you call them till their bellies is full and their
bellies is bottomless. And when they do get them full, they won't hear you then.
For then they sink in the sea, go fast asleep on the coral, and can't hear
nothing at all, no more, forever and ever.
Upon my soul, I am about the same opinion. So give the benediction,
fleece, and I'll away to my supper.
Upon this fleece, holding both hands over the fishy mob, raised his shrill
voice and cried, "Cursed fellow critters, kick up the damnedest row as
ever you can. Fill your damn bellies till they burst, and then die." "Now
cook," said Stub, resuming his supper at the capston. "Stand just where you stood
before there, over against me, and pay particular attention."
All tension, said Fleece again, stooping over his tongs in the desired position.
Well, said Stub, helping himself freely.
Meanwhile, I shall now go back to the subject of this stake. In the first
place, how old are you, Cook? What that to do with the take? said the old black
testy. Silence. How old are you, Cook?
About 90, they say, he gloomily muttered. and you have lived in this
world hard upon 100 years, cook, and don't know yet how to cook a whale
steak, rapidly bolting another mouthful at the last word, so that morsel seemed
a continuation of the question. Where were you born, cook? And a hatchway in
ferryboat going over to Rowan Oak. Born in a ferryboat? That's queer, too. But I
want to know what country you were born in, cook. Didn't I say to Rowan Oak
country? He cried sharply. No, you didn't, Cook. But I'll tell you what I'm
coming to, cook. You must go home and be born over again. You don't know how to
cook a whale steak yet. Rest my soul if I cook another one, he growled angrily,
turning round to depart. Come back here, cook. Here, hand me those tongs. Now
take that bit of steak there and tell me if you think that steak cooked as it
should be. Take it, I say, holding the tongs toward him. Take it and taste it.
Faintly smacking his withered lips over it for a moment. The old negro muttered.
Best cook I ever taste. Juicy. Very juicy. Cook, said Stubs, squaring
himself once more. Do you belong to the church? passed one once in Cape Town,
said the old man sullenly.
And you have once in your life passed a holy church in Cape Town, where you
doubtless overheard a holy parson addressing his hearers as his beloved
fellow creatures have you, Cook. And yet you come here and tell me such a
dreadful lie as you did just now. Eh, said Stub. Where do you expect to go to,
Cook? Go to bed very soon," he mumbled, half turning as he spoke. "I've asked
heave, too. I mean, when you die, cook."
It's an awful question. Now, what's your answer?
When this old black man dies, said the negro slowly, changing his whole air and
demeanor. He himself won't go nowhere, but some breasted angel will come and
fetch him. Fetch him? How? in a coach and four as they fetched Elijah. And
fetch him where? Up there, said Fleece, holding his tongue straight over his
head and keeping it there very solemnly.
So then, you expect to go up into our main top, do you, cook, when you are
dead? But don't you know the higher you climb, the colder it gets? Main top? Eh?
Didn't say that at all, said Fleece again in the sulks. You said upper,
didn't you? And now look yourself and see where your tongs are pointing. But
perhaps you expect to get into heaven by crawling through the lover's hole, Cook.
But no, no, Cook, you don't get there except you go the regular way, round by
the rigging. It's a ticklish business, but it must be done or else it's no go.
But none of us are in heaven yet. Drop your tongs, cook, and hear my orders. Do
you hear? Hold your hat in one hand and clap the other a top your heart when I'm
giving my orders. Cook. What? That your heart there? That's your gizzard. A
loft. A loft. That's it. Now you have it. Hold it there now and pay attention.
all attention," said the old black, with both hands placed as desired, vainly
wriggling his grizzled head as if to get both ears in front at one in the same
time. "Well, then, cook, you see this whale steak of yours was so very bad
that I have put it out of sight as soon as possible. You see that, don't you?
Well, for the future, when you cook another whale steak for my private table
here, the capston, I'll tell you what to do so as not to spoil it by overdoing.
Hold the steak in one hand and show a live coal to it with the other. That
done, dish it. Do you hear? And now, tomorrow, cook, when we are cutting in
the fish, be sure you stand by to get the tips of his fins. Have them put in
pickle. As for the ends of the flukes, have them sousted, cook, there, now you
may go. But Fleece had hardly got three paces off when he was recalled. Cook,
give me cutlets for supper tomorrow night in the midwatch. Do you hear? Away
you sail, then. Hello. Stop. Make a bow before you go. Avast heaving again.
Whale balls for breakfast. Don't forget wish Bore whale eat him instead of him
eat whale. I'm breast if he ate more of shark than maza shark himself muttered
the old man limping away with which sage ejaculation he went to his hammock.